A Guide to the Mecklenburg County (Va.) Chancery Causes,, 1783-1944 (bulk 1870-1912)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Mecklenburg County (Va.) Chancery Causes,, 1783-1944 (bulk 1870-1912)
Library of Virginia
155.7 cubic feet (343 boxes); Digital images.
Mecklenburg County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Chancery Causes, 1783-1872 use digital images found electronically on the Chancery Records Index available on the website of the Library of Virginia.
Chancery Causes 1873-1944 are processed and indexed information is available on the Chancery Records Index, but digital images are not at this time. Contact Archives Research Services for availability
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Mecklenburg Circuit Court in an undated accession.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case; however, the judge is basing the descison on findings compiled and documented by Commissioners. Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history. Chancery causes document the lived experiences of free and enslaved individuals; women; children; people living with physical disabilities or mental health struggles; people living in poverty; defunct institutions and corporate entities; or those that may not have otherwise left traditional written histories.
Locality History: Mecklenburg County (Va.) was named for Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz, consort of King George III. It was formed from Lunenburg County in 1764. The county court first met on 11 March 1765. The county seat is Boydton.
Scope and Content
Mecklenburg County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1782-1944, consists of cases concerning issues of equity brought largely by residents of the county and filed in the circuit court. These cases often involve the following actions: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, disputes regarding contracts, debt, divorce, and business disputes. Other less prevalent issues include freedom suits, permissions to sell property, and disputes concerning trespass. Predominant documents found in these chancery causes include bills (documents the plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response to the plaintiff's complaint), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, plats, wills, records involving enslaved individuals, business records or vital statistics.
The vast majority of causes represented in these record concern disputes over contracts, issues related to debt, or causes concerning estates.
In the causes pre-1865, there is a substantial amount of information concerning enslaved Black men, women, and children. While there are several suits concerning the freedom of enslaved individuals, these cases largely represent the perspective of white enslavers and their disputes involving the sale, hiring, financial responsibilities, and legality of ownership of Black individuals. Specifically, there are many cases concerning estate disputes which over enslaved individuals.
While not a large number of divorce cases included in these records, many of these suits contain racial components and interracial relationships.
Additionally, there are various courts represented in these causes including causes heard in Superior Chancery and Superior Law and Chancery of the Richmond and Henrico Districts.
Arrangement
Organized by case, of which each is assigned a unique index number comprised of the latest year found in case and a sequentially increasing 3-digit number assigned by the processor as cases for that year are found. Arranged chronologically.
Arrangement of documents within each folder are as follows: Bill, Answer, and Final Decree (if found.)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Mecklenburg County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. Consult A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm.
Mecklenburg County is one of Virginia's Lost Records Localities. Additional Mecklenburg County Records may be found in the Lost Records Localities Digital Collection available on the Library of Virginia website.
Selected Causes of Interest
Causes of Interest are identified by local records archivists during processing and indexing. These causes are generally selected based upon guiding principles of having historical, genealogical or sensational significance; however, determining what is "of interest" is subjective, and the individual perspective and experience of the describing archivist will affect the material identified.
- 1804-025: Robert Hyde v. Dr. Samuel Griffin:
  Robert Hyde seeks an injunction on a judgement obtained by Samuel Griffin for account owed by Hyde to Griffin. However, Hyde claims Griffin intentionally killed the child of a woman Hyde enslaved during delivery and subsequently advised Hyde to sell the woman for she could not deliver children through the normal process. Hyde states he sold the woman at a great loss and has learned the woman has since given birth to multiple healthy children, indicating Griffin fraudulently advised him resulting in a financial loss greatly than the account he supposedly owes.
- 1833-010: Edward B. Hicks, etc. v. Alexander Boyd, etc.
  1833-010: Edward B. Hicks, etc. v. Alexander Boyd, etc. While the main issue of this cause regards existing debt between the involved parties, there are numerous enslaved individuals mentioned many with noted occupations. Enslaved individuals referenced were enslaved at "Allens Creek Plantation", "Butchers Creek plantation", "Maherin plantation," and other properties owned by Alexander Boyd. Enslaved individuals with occupations include: Simon, Caesar, and Charles (Waggoners); Ambrose and Tom (Millers); Fed and Anthony (Coopers); Edmond, Charles, and Matt (Blacksmiths); Shaderick and Nathan (Shoemakers); Caesar (Bricklayer); Kit (Carpenter); James (Wheelwright); Moses (Hatter or Haller); Henry (Tanner); and Edmond (Carriage Driver).
- 1833-034: William T. Pennington v. Admr of Howell Pennington, etc.
  William T. Pennington is a resident of Brunswick County, and claims "undue influence" of Martha Pennington Harper on her cousin, Howel Pennington. Martha received anywhere between a dozen to 30 enslaved individuals from estate of Howel Pennington. Other heirs of Howel Pennington lived in the western country. Longbottom's deposition discusses Howel Pennington executing a deed of emancipation "for his black people." Record in cause come from Superior Court of Chancery, Richmond District. Decree comes from Superior Court of Chancery, Henrico County. See also: 1839-011 and 1840-016.
- 1837-019: Admx of Sarah Draper, etc. v. William Green & wife, etc.
  Defendant William Green was the administrator of Dorothy Ripley, a native of Yorkshire County, England and a Quaker. Mary Ann, William Green's wife, was the sister of William Ripley, a nephew of Dorothy Ripley. Dorothy Ripley's brother John was a mason & bricklayer in England. Great deal of correspondence with Quaker genealogy.
- 1837-022: Nathaniel T. Green, etc. v. George T. Taylor, etc.
  Nathaniel T. Green, James H. Taylor and George T. Taylor formed a co-partnership initially to mine gold in the state of North Carolina. The mine operated by enslaved labor, those named include Shack, Mary Ann, Liliah (or Lelah, who worked while pregnant), Absalom (mentioned he was a "runaway"), Betsey, and Ben. An account book from the mine is included in the suit. See the story of Burke County Gold Rush: North Carolina Historical Review, Volume 40, No.4, pp. 489-500.
- 1837-035 John W.S. Northington, Rep v. Amy Wilkerson, etc.
  Plaintiff argued case before Congress regarding the petition of defendant's father "for a stud horse Romulus impressed into the service of the United States during the Revolutionary War." Plaintiff was successful in the case and defendant as heir to David Dardin was to receive $1500.00. In Congressional Record, defendant is identified as wife of David Dardin. [Suit Referenced in: Volume 3879 of US Congress Serial Set (p. 553, 585); and Jan. 27, 1832, Register of Debates in Congress, 22nd Congress, 1st session, (pp. 1670-1674)]
- 1848-006: John Barnes & wife, etc v. Admr. of James Batte, etc
  Estate dispute, which contains a large number of enslaved names with significant genealogical information for the enslaved community.
- 1848-018: Ritter,etc. (enslaved) vs Exr. of John Brummell
  Ritter and his children Elenor, Eliza, Francis, James, John Wright, Martha, Thoms, and Henry, are all enslaved individuals suing for their freedom.
- 1853-019: William N. Smith v. Abel W. Allen, etc
  William Smiths seeks to reverse a judgment at law found against him. The judgement found Smith guilty of slandering Abel Allen; however, Smith claims that Allen supplied the jury in the case with large amounts of liquor. Smith asserts this jury tampering is want secured the verdict against him in the case.
- 1857-018: Sallie A. Seymour, By etc. v. Mansfield R. Seymour
  Divorce case in which Sallie A. Seymour alleges that Mansfield Seymour, her husband, for years add extramarital relations with women enslaved by Mansfield and with a free Black woman. Sallie is granted a divorce as well as significant portion of estate, a number of enslaved individuals, and money. [similar to 1858-022 Lucy Burwell, by etc. vs John A. Burwell]
- 1864-013: Petition of Samuel D. Booker Comt., etc.
  Samuel Booker, acting as committee of Ann Jane Watkins, labeled "a lunatic," seeks to invest $1,000 of her funds in Confederate bonds. Confederate bond included in folder.
- 1868-014: William O. Baskerville by etc., vs. Gdn. William O Baskerville, etc.
  Suit in which complainant seeks to construct "a building which would accommodate a white family" on property for rent, which currently contains housing for Black families and individuals.
- 1868-024: Valentine B. Hudson, etc. vs. Cephas Hudson etc.
  Estate dispute in which Valentine Hudson and other plaintiffs argue that Charles Hudson's will is null and void since it was written when decedent was a felon and to be imprisoned. [Charles died in the State penitentiary serving a 18 year sentence for murder of Jane, a woman he enslaved. See: Staunton Vindicator, Volume 16, Number 41, 12 October 1860 for information on the murder case.]
- 1869-042: Humberston Reamy vs. William H. Blanch, Comt., etc.
  Humberston Reamy complains that through legal proceeding she was committed to Lunatic Asylum at Williamsburg [Eastern State Hospital] from 1858-1861, and upon his release returned to his wife and home only to find his property in a shambles. Reamy seeks restitution from William Blank, the sheriff and his committee, in addition to others who were securities on a bond with Blanch.
- 1869-056: Frederick Ivey, etc. vs. William Mitchell, etc.
  A Estate dispute spanning generations which centers the estate of the elder Frederick Ivey (1743-1821) and Priscilla "Prissy" Stewart (1777-1856). Court records do not specify Priscilla's race, but 1868-1869 correspondence of granddaughter's representative (power of attorney) references that Priscilla had been "colored," and that the couple's grandchildren live in Ohio near "a colored school & academy managed exclusively by colored people." A deposition of Thomas Wall in 1860, references George Ivey's, one of Frederick Ivey's sons, arrest and imprisonment as well as the sale of an enslaved child arranged by Priscilla Ivey.
- 1871-079: William Townes Sr., etc. v. Trsts. of Randolph Macon College
  Contract dispute where the plaintiffs seek intervention from the court to prevent the removal of Randolph Macon College from Boydton, Va., the Ashland, Va.
- 1872-007: Hannah Stewart, etc. v. Heirs of Rebecca Chavis, etc.
  Estate dispute which contains a great deal of genealogical information about the Free African American family of Dr. Thomas Stewart. Heirs of the family resided in Dinwiddie, Mecklenburg and Lunenburg counties and the cities of Norfolk and Richmond in Virginia as well as the states of Ohio, Tennessee, North Carolina, and Indiana.
- 1893-027: Mattie Goode by etc vs. Thomas Frank Goode
  Mattie Goode seeks a divorce on the grounds that Thomas "Frank" Goode is a "hermaphrodite," a fact she did not know prior to their marriage. The bill and depositions also detail Goode's "passions for men" and his killing of a woman [Rosa Couch] only serval days after the wedding. Upon him being released on the grounds of the murder being "accidental," Mattie Goode state's Frank fled to Pennslyivania and has not returned.